我们开始吧。这是Apple //e(Apple 2e) 一切就绪
Here we go. okay I see apple //e and we're ready to go
我想做一个非常简短的视频，大概十分钟左右
all right so I wanted to do a very quick video maybe ten minutes or so
介绍一下1981年的编程方式
talking about programming like it's 1981
好像很多观众都特别想知道当时是如何在 Apple 2 上编程的
in particular, a lot of people seem to have questions about how exactly you would have programmed the Apple 2 back in the day
我会先演示一下没有辅助工具之前的样子
And I want to show you what it looked like before you had tools
之后再演示一些非常基本的工具
Then I'll show you some of the very basic tools
如果有时间的话，我还会展示一下汇编程序的样子
And then I'll show you maybe if we have time what an assembler looks like
这里已经启动了Apple 2e 的模拟器( Windows下可以用 AppleWin )，我将按下重置按钮
So here we've got our Apple 2e running an emulation, I'm gonna hit the reset button
因为没有挂载磁盘，我们暂时看不到DOS界面
As if we have no no disc in the drive at all and here we are, we have no DOS
什么事都干不了，目前只有苹果内置的基础解释器工具
I can't look at anything, anything about anything all we have is the Apple soft basic interpreter which was built-in tool*
如你所愿，我们可以写一个小的演示程序
so we could write a small basic program just like you'd expect to see.
和每个人都会编写的基本程序一样，
The the basic program that everyone runs.
没啥意思
That's not very interesting
大家肯定会在 Apple 2 上玩游戏
sooner or later what everyone did on the Apple 2 of course was play games.
部分游戏中有BUG，并且当游戏崩溃时
some of those games had bugs and when the game crashed
如果它是BASIC游戏，有时可能会回到BASIC界面
you would sometimes into basic if it were basic game.
但是如果它是用机器语言编写的，可能会出现一个不常见的星号提示符
but if it were written in machine language you might drop to an unfamiliar prompt and that prompt would look like an asterisk
实际上它长这样，显示时通常伴随着"哔"的声音。
in fact it will looked like this typically beep
这个提示符有什么用？我们可以尝试获得一些帮助，
and what is this prompt?Well, we can try and get some help
发出了一个"哔"声，我们可以输入help和H
we got a beep. We could type help,H
就像UNIX系统中的VI编辑器一样
this is just like the VI editor if you're in UNIX
这是Apple2 机器语言的监视器*
what is this thing? Well,this is the Apple 2 machine language monitor.
这意味着你可以查看并修改内存中的值，所以先尝试输入一个数字
So monitor means that you can inspect and change things in memory so let's try typing a number ok
实际上这是内存中的第0个字节
So that is literally the zeroeth byte in memory
你也可以这么做
You can also do that
可以看到它的值是4C
And we see that it contains the value 4C
我们可以查看内存中的其他区域，最大地址好像是ffff
we can inspect other areas of memory we can go probably up to ffff.
*这实际上将在ROM存储器中( Apple 2e 的默认RAM是64kB)
which would be the probably that would actually be in the ROM memory as opposed to the RAM we can expect
可以用.的方式来一次查看内存中的多个字节
we can inspect multiple bytes in memory by using the *doc here, I can say show me all the memory there
如果你之前看过hexdump文件
And if you've ever seen a hex dump
你可能会发现这个输出显示了第一行是第0到第7字节
You might recognize this so this is showing us the first row is bytes 0 through 7
字节0的值是4C，字节1的值是3C
and byte0 contains 4C byte1 contains 3C
显示方式很好，但我们怎么操作它呢
so you know this is *cute but what can we actually do with it?
我们不仅能观察内存值，以0800处的内存为例
Well, we can't just look at memory so there I'm looking at byte 800
顺便说一下，这些数字在这里都是十六进制的
And these all numbers here are hexadecimal by the way.
我们还能修改它。比如将0800处字节的值从0改为99
We can change them. I could say well instead of having 0, I want 800 to have this byte 99
再次查看0800，可以看到内存被修改了
And now if I look at it again I just changed memory.
给640字节赋一个值
I'm gonna poke a value into byte 640 here.
这里还是把620字节的值改为55更好
Up here, actually let me to use a better value I'm gonna poke value 55.
您应该会在屏幕顶部看到一个闪烁的U
All right, you should see a blinking U up towards the top screen
这是哪来的? 让我们重复一次，让我们把相同的值再次赋值给原来的位置
Where did it come from well let's do it again let's put that value on the same byte on memory
出现了另一个闪烁的U
And there's another U
发生了什么？
so what just happened
不像现在的现代计算机有所谓的"受保护的内存"
Well unlike today's modern machines which have what's called protected memory
在类似Apple2 这样的8位计算机上，你有权限访问系统中的所有内存
on an 8-bit computer  like the Apple 2 you have complete access to all the memory in the system
这意味着你可能会让你心态爆炸或者把系统玩崩
which means you can really *hose yourself you could break things quite badly
但大多数设备将内存映射到内存中的某个区域
but most devices would be what's called memory mapped to some region in memory
所以我们在这里看到的屏幕文本实际上是从
so the text screen which is what we're looking at here is actually mapped from I want to say values
可能是400到7ff的值，大概是这样
I want to say values from say 400 to 7ff,I think something like that.
通常情况，你需要去查一下具体的地址值。
normally you would look this up if you want to know
当我把620字节的值改为55时，那个闪烁的U就代表55这个值
when I changed byte 620 to 55, it poked that value that flashing U is the value 55
将值修改为56，现在就显示一个闪烁的V字母
That is 56 now. It's a flashing V
如果我们修改多个字节的值
If I say,let's do some multiple bytes.
如果把610字节及其之后的内存值分别改为53 54 55 56 57 58，就可以看到闪烁的STUVW
610 53 54 55 56 57 58 and there you could see the flashing STUVW
我们可以查看和修改内存，你可能会觉得这没什么了不起的
All right so we can look at memory and we can change memory so what? What's the big deal?
这个监视器实际上可以做一些更有趣的事情
Well the monitor actually does some more interesting things.
它可以执行反汇编操作
in particular it can disassemble code
来看一下800内存地址处，这是通常是程序开始执行的入口
So let's look memory location 800 again which is a very common location for programs to begin
不要直接按回车，而是在末尾添加一个L
and instead of just hitting return here, I'm going to add an L on the end
可以看到监视器试图反汇编代码中的这些字节（例如6502的机器语言）
And now could see the monitor trying to disassemble the bytes that are in code as if they are 6502 machine language.
这些数据也许不一定是6502的机器代码，
now they might not actually be 6502 machine language
通常情况下可能只是普通的数据，就像我之前输入的值一样
Usually might be data just as I poked a value into the text
只是因为解释器刚好能将这些数据当做6502的汇编代码来输出
Maybe this is just some data that happened you might be able to interpret it as 6502 assembly
让我们实际操作一下
but we can actually show this in action
先在监视器里现场写一些汇编代码
so let's go ahead and write some assembly code in the monitor live
先把这些数据清理掉
so first I'm going to go ahead and clear this out
这里一大堆的 00 都被翻译为BRK指令
just throw a bunch of zero zeros in there which should be interpreted as the instruction break
有种更快的方法可以一次修改一段内存
there's a faster way to do a region memory
老实说我有点忘了，毕竟已经过去了30年
I'll be honest it has been 30 years I don't quite remember
可以看到这段内存都被显示为了BRK
Now I could see we got a bunch of breaks here
如果没有汇编程序和其他工具，你要怎么做呢
so what you would do before you had tools,before you had an assembler
你会拿到一本笔记本，还可能有一张速查卡，其中列出了6502指令集的操作码
you get a notebook and you will probably have a quick reference card listing all of the op codes of the 6502 instruction set
然后使用汇编语言编写程序
and you would write your program in assembly language
在一页的左侧位置上书写要实现的功能
kind of longhand what you think you would want to do on the left side of the paper
在同一页的右侧，先要查找操作码，就像在计算尺上查找对数一样
and on the right side of the paper you would look up the opcode like you were looking up a logarithm with a slide rule
之后将操作码写在右侧
and you would write the opcode on the right-hand side
实际上，还有专门的帮助手册
there are actually special pads of paper to help you do this
因为当时8位计算机是非常普遍的
because it was so such a common thing to do with 8-bit computers
现在来编写一个没有具体作用的程序
I'm going to write a useless program right now
只是几行没有具体功能的汇编代码
That just a couple lines of assembly code it doesn't do anything useful
我其实准备了一些后续的程序，但我不打算在这期视频中说太多
I have some programs that I have prepared for future ones of these but they don't want to go too long
写入我的内存的一个操作码是A9，代表加载累加器立即数模式（LDA）
so let's go so the one opcode that is burned into my memory is a9 which stands for load the accumulator immediate mode
可以取一个值，比如55
and you could take a value let's take 55
如果我们看一下反汇编这段代码的结果
And just say that and now if we look if we disassemble this code
在屏幕顶端我们可以看见左侧是A9 55 右侧是 LDA #$55（十六进制）
we can see the top line of the screen there it says a9 55 on the left and load the accumulator pound/dollar hex 55
表示向累加器加载值0x55
load the accumulator with the value 55
让我们再增加一些数据 (40年后的苹果手机铃声)
let's also then add some more
记不清是8D还是85了，先试下8D
let's try I can't remember it's 8D or 85 let's try an 8d
...40 06 希望这是一个有效的操作码
40 06, I hope that's a vaild opcode,
我没有使用速查卡，只是随意浏览一下
I'm actually not using quick reference card right now so I'm kind of doing this kind of surfing here
好了，可以看到在0x802地址中的指令已经将累加器的值存储在0x64这个内存地址中
alright so we can see that in memory location 802 we have stored the accumulator in memory location 64
继续向累加器载入值，比如0x42
so let's go ahead and do some more * load the accumulator with another value how about I don't know 42
可以继续在当前行输入值
and let's go ahead and just continue we can continue to type memory in here
这些值还是会写入之后的内存，我们将其存储在41 06地址中
we just poking values of memory and we'll store that in 41 06
这两个字节的先后顺序和实际值是相反的，原因是处理器的字节序（小端）
these are byte swapped because of the endianness of the processor
我们的四行汇编语言程序，再加一行BRK指令作为结尾
all right so now we have our four line assembly language program let's make it 5 lines and just finish it up with a break
然后就可以从Apple2监视器运行程序了
and so from the Apple 2 monitor you can run the program
动手运行吧
so let's go ahead and run the program
聊天室里的Patrick说他现在能理解我为什么能忍受 Space Camp这种游戏了。的确如此。
Patrick in the chat says he now sees how I could stand to play things like Space Camp, yes exactly
用G来运行程序，例如800G
so we're gonna say G, 800 G, go
我们运行了刚才的程序，它没什么具体作用，只是返回了一些状态标志
We just ran our progarm, it did't do much useful. when we ran it we got the status flags
展示了6502的寄存器，先说前三个
so this is showing us * registers of the 6502 there are three registers
A是累加器，用于算术运算。X Y寄存器通常用于索引和指针操作
the a is the accumulator the one register you can do arithmetic with, x and y are used for indexing generally for * pointer manipulating.
P是状态标志
P are the status flags
这是一个非常复杂的话题，今天就先不深入了
which are a really complicated topic beyond today's talk
下次有机会再说吧。S是堆栈指针。
get into that next time if we get there and S is the stack pointer
可以在标记为814的行上看到，00 BRK，然后是闪烁的UB字符
You can see up here on the line labeled 814 it says 00 BRK and then a flashing u and a flashing b
这就是我们刚才改变的内存位置，我们给它赋了个新值
that was the memory we just changed,we just poked the value into that memory *
如果查看那段内存，那些值还没有保存到内存里
now if I were to inspect that memory now those values wouldn't there
因为我将它们输入到文本域或者叫文本视图映射的内存区域
because I poked them into the text field or or the text view the text memory map and of course
我们正在改变的就是映射的内存区域，所以才能看到修改
here we are changing it so that we could see things
这是就最基本的监视器功能
so that's the monitor at its most basic
做得更好，并且很快苹果做了一点
but we can do a little better and very quickly Apple
他们实现了一个叫 mini汇编器 的程序
they implemented something called the mini assembler.
每个人都知道监视器，因为迟早会因为程序崩溃而进入监视器界面
everyone knows about the monitor because sooner or later you crashed and ended up in it
但很少人知道 mini汇编器
fewer people know about the mini-assembler
mini汇编程序可以协助我们完成刚才的编程，免去查找操作码的麻烦
a mini-assembler helps you do what we just did but without having to look up the opcodes,hopefully.
尝试进入mini汇编器
you enter the mini assembler
我觉得现在无法进入mini汇编器，因为我已经加载了一张磁盘
actually I think we won't able to do it here because I do load a disk
哦其实运行成功了，因为我们现在用的是Apple 2e
Oh look at that it's actually run because this is an apple 2e
如果用的是Apple 2 或者plus ,就需要加载磁盘。但我们可以直接开始
so on an Apple 2 or plus you would have had to load a disk to do this but and we were able to do
让我们输入一些内容
so let's see what happens here if we say...
补充一下，我刚才输入了800：
great, so in case you missed what happened there I typed 800 :
然后是A9 99，它立即将其翻译成操作码并显示出结果
and then a9 99 like that and it immediately translated it into the opcode and kind of displayed results.
我觉得如果输入冒号，就可以继续操作后续的内存。试试对不对
so I think if I type a colon I can keep going. let's see if that's true
让我们看看是否正确，让我们尝试将其存储在地址为300的内存中
let's try and store this in memory location 300
不行
no it doesn't like that
哦原来只要输入一个空格就好了
Oh, that's just a space,okay.
我们将0x99存储在地址为300的内存中，之后加载值88
so then we're storing that 99 in memory location 300 let's continue let's load value 88
将a转移到X寄存器
and let's store let's transfer a to the X register
将X寄存器的值保存到地址为301的内存中，目前的操作还比较无趣
and then let's store register in memory location 301 so I'm not that interesting you know
我觉得要按下“重置”按钮（模拟器中是Ctrl+F2）离开mini汇编器
I believe we have to hit the reset button to leave the mini assembler
这就是我们的程序了
We're looking our program there it is
在运行之前，先看下 300和301内存
we'll run our program first let's look at memory locations 300 and 301
它们的值是FF。然后运行程序
they contain FF let's run our program
再次查看内存300 301，可以看到它们的值是99和88
And let's look at memory locations 300 301 again and you can see they contain 99 and 88
mini汇编器实际上只是一个翻译程序，它可以动态翻译
the mini-assembler is really just a translator it's translating completely on the fly
可以输入注释，但汇编器不会保留注释，也没有文件管理功能
you can type comments it won't keep them there's no file management here
要么写入，要么丢失
there just stuff is in and gone forever
如果需要写代码量很多的大程序
so to write a program at significant length if you're not laws*
就需要一个真正的汇编器，包括支持注释的编辑器
you really need a program a real assembler that will have a nice editor will let you add comments
还要能支持元数据，这样就可以编写变量。
have meta things so you could have variables
如果你在1978年买了一台苹果电脑，就只能用这些基础功能。当时还没有为其开发的优秀软件。
but this is the basics this is what you got if you bought an apple in 1978 before there was really any good software for it.
在当时，你只能这么编程
software for it this was the type of programming you could do
但这已经是一次像KIM-1那样的飞跃了，因为
this was a leap above things like the KIM-1
因为它可以显示出操作代码
because you actually had a display on which you could see the op
这些就是我想给出的基本介绍了
so that is the basic intro that I wanted to give
很少涉及汇编语言编程，因为这方面的资源已经很多了。
Not so much about how to programming assembly language because I think there's tons of resources about that
只是让大家感受一下在没有编程工具时如何编程
just the the feel of what it was like to try to do these things before tools existed
如果有下一期的话，我打算加载一个我可能用到的汇编器
if I do another one of these I think the next step would be to load a assembler I would probably use.
叫做Merlin 并展示它
Merlin and show it
要我现在演示吗?还是下次再说？（作者在Youtube直播）
should we should we save that till next time
那继续吧，YouTube的直播可能会中断
I'm gonna go ahead and I'll do it now I might break the video here for YouTube
就当做直播观众的独家内容好了
But just for the people who are watching I think
插入磁盘，希望能用
let's just stick a disc in here and hopefully it will actually work.
我大概有八个版本的Merlin
I've like eight versions of Merlin
等待加载中
Waiting for it to load,
我把仿真程序的处理速度设置为Apple 2的实际速度，所以慢得离谱
I have the emulator set to actual speed of an Apple 2 which is hideously slow of course
这就是Merlin的界面了，可以看到这里有各种处理文件的选项，让我们深入一下
so here we are in Merlin,you can see that there's various options here dealing with files let's just dive right in
按e编辑文件，进入一个堪用的行编辑器
hit e to edit file we get more or less a line editor I'm
按a添加一行，增加程序入口
A to add a line okay we can tell it where we want our program to make it exactly
写一个和刚才功能一样的程序
Let's make it exactly the same as the one we just did
输入 空格 ORG $0800
so we'll say ORG dollar 800
这不是一个6502指令集的操作码，只是一个给汇编程序的提示符
this is not a 6502 opcode that's a hint to the assembler
还可以自定义一些符号，比如head等于0300 tail等于0301
we could also define some symbols so let's say head is equal to 0300, tail is equal to 0301
还能增加注释
we can have comments this awesome program write some values
然后就按你自己的习惯写代码
And then we just write our code as as we'd like to
最难的部分其实是使用这样的行编辑器，这比写汇编让人烦躁
the hardest part of doing this would actually be using a line editor like this
因为我们已经习惯了使用现代的全屏幕编辑器了
full-screen editors we're all used to today
我想把它保存在地址为300的内存中，所以使用自定义的符号名称
so I want to store this in memory location 300 so I'll just use the symbolic name i defined
值为88，然后转移到寄存器Y
In fact I will say 88 whatever they say  transferred to the Y register this time
将寄存器Y的值存储在tail地址，然后用BRK结束这段代码。
store Y in tail and then we'll finish up with a break
不是个很有趣的程序，但我喜欢探索不同的方式
Okay not a very interesting program but I want to stick with doing the same thing in different ways
在空白行处换行
hey I hit return on an empty line here.
这样就可以汇编代码了
now I can assemble the program
因为我阅读过文档，所以我知道能这么做
In this case I happen to know because I read the documentation
顺便提一句，缺少在线帮助是早期的Apple 2程序的一致特点
the lack of online help by the way is a consistent feature of early Apple 2 programs
没有手册就无法完成任何事情
you simplely could not get anything done without the manual
那时电脑上的内存非常有限，因此大多数程序都没有内置在线帮助功能
The memory you had on the computer was so limited that the add-on online help system to most of programs
没有足够空间给你的程序使用
you wouldn't have room for your program
执行汇编，这个问题选择“否”
so let's go ahead and assemble it I'm answering no to that question
可以看到上面有一堆操作码，展示了整个程序的样子，还显示了一些自定义符号
You could see bunch of op codes up here it kind of shows us what it looked like it mentions that we have a few symbols
现在应该退出，这样就可以保存源代码
and then I think we want to quit so we can now save the source code.
文件名就叫TESTPROG
let's just call it test program
这样就储存为TESTPROG.S，S代表汇编语言。接下来保存目标代码
Is gonna save that as TESTPROG dot s s for assembly language we can then save the object code
这是我们将要实际运行的程序
Which is our actual program that we're going to run
但愿能跑。我要退出梅林了，让我们来看一下磁盘
hopefully this will work I'm going to quit out of the out of Merlin let's look at our disk
一堆代码
A bunch of stuff here
我把它直接保存在了汇编器的磁盘上，不是很讲究
Of course I save that right to the assembler disk which is not very cool
返回监视器，确保程序不在内存中。可以看到它确实不在内存里
let's just really quickly drop into the monitor make sure that the program is not in memory you can see it's not
一堆BRK语句，所以内存是空的，让我们运行程序
bunch of breaks so memory is empty and let's run our run we'll run it all at once
用BRUN运行，它将一次运行所有名叫TESTPROG的程序
just use brun we'll run it all at once what do they call it TESTPROG
寄存器的值看起来是正确的，我们的程序实现了预期的功能
we can see the registers already look correct our program did what it was supposed to do
这些工具的优缺点如上所述。1978年到1982年的编程工具就是这样的。
That's the long and short of it this is kind of what the tools looked like in 1978 to 1982
随着时间的推移，工具越来越完善
and they got better over time you'll see that
如果你对比一张磁盘上不同版本的Merlin，就可以看到它是如何逐渐改进的。
If you pick up versions of Merlin from one of the Apple 2 disk archives you can see how it improves overtime
随着时间的推移，他们得到了神族的支持，最终得到了真正的满足。
they had a * support eventually they got a real full screen editor
屏幕编辑器而不是行编辑器，但这确实是一个不同的世界
screen editor instead of a line editor but it's it's really a different world
如果再出一个类似的视频，我将会写一个实际的程序
and if I do another one of these I think the next one will be writing an actual program
尝试解释6502的一些变化
and trying to one explain some of the vagaries at the 6502
即使在汇编语言层面上，该CPU上的编程也不同于其他拥有更多特性的CPU
how programming even in assembly language is different on that CPU than on a let's say more * feature CPU
我还会试着让你感受当时的各种困难条件
and second I might try to motivate why would anyone put themselves through this
一言以蔽之 Apple 2 太慢了
and the one sentence answer is man the Apple 2 was really really slow
因此，任何通过直接的汇编编程带来的速度优势都是非常有价值的
and so any speed advantage you can get by directly an assembly language was super valuable
我们下次可以举一个例子来说明
we can go through an example * next time
这就是本次全部内容了，感谢收看
that's it. thanks for tuning in
和你们一起在内存受限的小路上闲逛很不错，我们下次再见！
and it's good taking this stroll down memory constrained lane with you, bye!